<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true account of the heroick actions and enterprises of the confederate princes against the Turks and Hungarian rebels, during the last glorious campaign but more particularly the siege and taking of Newheusel. Together with the defeat of the Turkish army near Gran. To which is added the flight and seizure of the grand rebel, Count Teckely, by the Turks; and the manner of his treatment. Licensed Novemb. 19. 1685. Ro. L'Estrange.</title>
            <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60019</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831704</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831704</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60019)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2098:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true account of the heroick actions and enterprises of the confederate princes against the Turks and Hungarian rebels, during the last glorious campaign but more particularly the siege and taking of Newheusel. Together with the defeat of the Turkish army near Gran. To which is added the flight and seizure of the grand rebel, Count Teckely, by the Turks; and the manner of his treatment. Licensed Novemb. 19. 1685. Ro. L'Estrange.</title>
                  <author>J. S. (John Shirley), fl. 1680-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for William Thackery in Duck-lane, Thomas Passinger on London-Bridge, and Tho. Sawbridge in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Preface to the reader" signed: John Shirley.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thököly, Imre, --  gróf, 1657-1705 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Mehmed IV, 1648-1687 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hungary --  History --  Turkish occupation, 1526-1699 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE ACCOUNT OF THE Heroick Actions and Enterpriſes OF THE Confederate Princes Againſt the TURKS AND HUNGARIAN REBELS, During the laſt glorious Campaign; But more particularly the Siege and taking of <hi>NEWHEUSEL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with the Defeat of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army near <hi>GRAN.</hi> To which is added the Flight and Seizure of the Grand Rebel, <hi>COUNT TECKELY,</hi> By the <hi>Turks;</hi> and the manner of his Treatment.</p>
            <p>Licenſed <hi>Novemb.</hi> 19. 1685. Ro. <hi>L'Eſtrange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Thackery</hi> in <hi>Duck-lane, Thomas Paſſenger</hi> on <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Sawbridge</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1686.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:36171:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36171:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN this ſmall Book you have an Impartial Account of the moſt conſiderable Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Paſſages relating to the War, &amp;c. between the Confederate Princes, <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> Rebels, in divers parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> the Two precedent Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigns, as Sieges, Battels, Skirmiſhes, and Negotiations: but more particularly of the famous Sieges of <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> the Defeat of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army near <hi>Gran,</hi> the continued currant of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and glorious Succeſs of the King of
<pb facs="tcp:36171:3"/>
               <hi>Poland,</hi> the Surprize of Count <hi>Teckeley,</hi> and the Ruin of the Rebels Intereſt in the <hi>Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Hungary;</hi> Shewing the prevalence of the Chriſtian Arms againſt thoſe Infidels, and ſuch as were their Partakers: who for many years have deluged the once flouriſhing part of <hi>Europe</hi> with Blood, and committed ſuch out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages as have ſtartled Mankind. But the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of the wicked is but for a ſeaſon; which at length they have found; and that they may yet be made more ſenſible, that he whoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Name they impiouſly blaſpheme, will cruſh them' with a Rod of Iron, is the Wiſh of, Reader,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to ſerve you, <hi>JOHN SHIRLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:36171:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A TRUE ACCOUNT OF THE Heroick Actions and Enterpriſes OF THE CONFEDERATE PRINCES Againſt the <hi>TURKS</hi> and <hi>Hungarian</hi> REBELS, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Turks, Anno</hi> 1683. routed at <hi>Barkan,</hi> that place taken, and ſoon after <hi>Gran,</hi> the Campaign drew to a Concluſion by reaſon of the Seaſon's Advancement, and the Soldiers were diſpoſed for their Winter-Quarters. The King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and other confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Princes retiring with the greateſt part of their Troops to their reſpective Countries, to be the better in a readineſs to take field early in the Spring; of which <hi>Teckely</hi> taking the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, fell in with the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Rear, killing 300. and taking ſome part of the Baggage; but being charged by the <hi>Lithuanian</hi> Troops, he was not only obliged to retreat with the loſs of a conſiderable number of his men, but to fly to the utmoſt Corner of the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> which gave the Imperialiſts opportunity to recover ſome Towns, and repair ſuch as were ruinous, as likewiſe to block up <hi>Newheuſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:36171:4"/>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> being thus put to the worſt, and in danger of loſing Footing in <hi>Hungary,</hi> the bad Conduct, as they alledged, that had run things into ſo great a Hazard, was imputed to <hi>Cera Muſtapha,</hi> the Grand Vizier, whoſe Head, to appeaſe the unruly multitude in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> the Grand Signior was obliged to ſend for by an <hi>Aga,</hi> who on the fifteenth day of <hi>December</hi> ſtrangled, or cauſed him to be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled in his Tent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1684. Early the enſuing Spring, the Imperial Army taking the Field, preſſed <hi>Newheuſel</hi> with much Reſolution; but the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> perceiving it a Work of great Difficulty, it was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at that time concluded to reduce it by Famine; and thereupon blocking it up, his Highneſs drew off the greateſt part of the Army to take in <hi>Vaccia</hi> and <hi>Novegrade,</hi> but found, upon his Arrival, that the <hi>Turks,</hi> to the number of twenty thouſand, had ſtrongly poſſeſt the Hills near <hi>Vaccia,</hi> under the leading of the Vizier of <hi>Buda,</hi> towards whom he marched in two Lines, about Eleven in the Morning, who kept their ſtation till he approached to the foot of the Hill, and then with their uſual Cries, deſcending, they charged the Regiment of <hi>Taff</hi> in the middle of the firſt Line, but the Duke being there in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they were beaten off. His Highneſs having his Horſe wounded, and two Officers killed with Piſtol-ſhot very near him; yet the <hi>Turks</hi> rallyed a ſecond and third time, but obſerving the firmneſs of the Chriſtians, they fell into Confuſion, and in the end to open Flight; but being hotly purſued, 3000 were ſlain 1500 taken Priſoners, with ſeven pieces of Cannon, eighteen Enſigns, the Vizier's Horſe, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, with two other Baſſa's, being killed; and amongſt the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners were found a Baſſa and ten <hi>Aga</hi>'s: or <hi>Zangiacks;</hi> the Imperialiſts in this Action not loſing above 100 men; and amongſt them none of Note. Whereupon <hi>Vaccia, Novegrade</hi> and ſoon, after Peſt, fell into the Hands of the Imperialiſts; ſo that whilſt Terror and Confuſion reigned amongſt the Infidels, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> calling a Council of of War, it was reſolved, <hi>Buda</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> chief Fortreſs in <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſhould be beſieged.</p>
            <p>The Reſolves of the Council of War being put in Practice, and the <hi>Turks</hi> who had ſet fire on the lower Town, beaten into the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Town, the Chriſtians poſſeſſed themſelves of divers ſtrong Poſts, and plaied from their Battery inceſſantly, the better to give the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners opportunity to run their Mines to the foot of the Bulwarks, and ſoon after ſent a Trumpet to ſummon the Baſſa-Governour to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render; whoſe Anſwer was, <hi>That he had Powder and Bullet to defend
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:36171:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>it; and would do it to the laſt extremity; knowing if he did otherwiſe, he ſhould be delivered into the hands of the Hangman, and ruin his Friends and Favourites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were doing, Count <hi>Teckeley</hi> took the Caſtle of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngwar,</hi> and put moſt of the Gentry he found therein to the Sword. But the Imperial Troops making head againſt him, he was forced to fly to the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Mongatz:</hi> And General <hi>Leſly,</hi> after a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Battery, and the overthrow of two <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Parties, that were coming to relieve it, had <hi>Virevitzi</hi> put into his poſſeſſion, the Garriſon conſiſting of Six Hundred <hi>Janizaries,</hi> having leave to March out with Bag and Baggage, the place having been in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Turks</hi> One Hundred and Thirteen Years. The <hi>Poles</hi> and <hi>Venetians</hi> being likewiſe abroad, defeated divers Parties of the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering many great Booties and Places of ſtrength; the latter taken after many furious Aſſaults. The City of <hi>Preveſa,</hi> aad the <hi>Morla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques,</hi> a People who have put themſelves under the protection of the <hi>Venetians</hi> made many Incurſions into <hi>Valachia</hi> and <hi>Moldavia;</hi> greatly endamaging the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Territories on that ſide.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> being by this time at the Head of his Troops before <hi>Buda,</hi> the Siege was carried on with great Courage and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; which obliged the beſieged on the <hi>17th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to make a Sally with their utmoſt ſtrength: whereby the Chriſtians that were in the Advance-works, were forced to give ground; but ſeconded by the next Guard, they ſoon returned upon the Enemy, and drove them with great ſlaughter into the Town, ſprung a Mine at the Root of their <hi>Attack-Baſtion,</hi> but it effected not the Execution intended: yet they lodged in the breach, forcing the Enemy thence: but for want of a conſiderable Number of Foot, durſt not attempt forcing their paſſage into the City. And now <hi>Cera Mahomet,</hi> the Governour, dying of his Wounds, it was expected the Place which was greatly ruined with the Cannon and Bombs, would have ſurrendered: But upon <hi>Ibraim Baſſa</hi>'s taking upon him the Government; and upon the approach of the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> with the Rallied Troops, the Garriſon was encouraged to hold out, though the Curtain between the Town and Caſtle, was rent in pieces, and the Houſes ſo miſerably burnt and ſhattered with the <hi>Bombs,</hi> that they, to prevent it for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, took off the firſt ſtories of the Houſes, and covered the reſt thick with Earth, laying ſtraw in the ſtreets, to prevent, as much as might be, the pieces of the Grannado-ſhells from doing Execution in their burſting.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36171:5"/>
            <p>General <hi>Scultz</hi> underſtanding what poſture Count <hi>Teckeley</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was in, reſolved to ſurprize him in his Camp, and marched with ſuch ſecrecy, that he came within <hi>Culverin</hi>-ſhot before he was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and fell upon the Rebels with ſuch fury, that all they could do, after ſome ſmall reſiſtance, was to ſave themſelves by flight, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Tents, Ammunition, and Baggage, tegether with the Coach, Standard, and private Letters of <hi>Teck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ley,</hi> who was forced to fly almoſt naked; and the <hi>German</hi> Cavalry hotly purſuing them, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were drowned in the River <hi>Tarza:</hi> ſo that Three Thouſand were reckoned to fall by the Sword, and ſmothered in the water: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them divers <hi>Hungarian</hi> Lords; the reſt, for the moſt part, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caping into <hi>Eſperies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Buda</hi> being cloſely preſſed by the Chriſtians, the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> uſed many Endeavours to relieve it by alarming the Beſiegers, often at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting with his Light Horſemen, to break through the Leaguer; but was as often prevented, and beat back with much ſlaughter: But the ſeaſon advancing, and the continual Rains hindering the <hi>Miners,</hi> as likewiſe a Mortal ſickneſs raging in the Camp, after all that could in ſuch Exigencies be done, on the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> a Council of War was held, in which it was reſolved, That the Emperor's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſent a little before, for raiſing the Siege, ſhould be obeyed. Whereupon all the ſick and wounded men, being near Eight Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, together with the Baggage and uſeleſs perſons, were ſent down the River, the Cannon taken from the Batteries, to ſecure the Retreat of the Troops, in their Retreat in the Iſle of St. <hi>Andrea,</hi> where the whole Army conſiſting of Thirty Thouſand men, paſſed the <hi>Danube</hi> the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> over a Bridg of Boats, the Cavalry fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the <hi>Seraſquier,</hi> whilſt the Foot Marched off; the Conduct of which was in ſuch good order, that neither the beſieged, nor the <hi>Seraſquier</hi>'s Army, durſt attack them. The Imperialiſt drawn off, the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> entered <hi>Buda,</hi> and cauſed the works the Beſiegers had rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to be demoliſhed; as likewiſe the Ruins of that place to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, the City, in a manner, being reduced to Aſhes and Rubbiſh, and muſt of neceſſity have fallen into the hands of the Chriſtians, had not the extremity of the weather contributed more to its defence than the Valour of the Beſieged, whoſe number was greatly decreaſed, and proviſion ſpent.</p>
            <p>And now the Chriſtians not thinking it worth while to keep Peſt and <hi>Vaccia,</hi> ſlighted them; and having well ſecured all places of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, leaving <hi>Newbeuſel</hi> blocked up, the Troops went into their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36171:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Quarters appointed in <hi>Hungary, Moravia, Sileſia,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi> And ſo ended this Campaign and Siege, in the latter of which, by ſickneſs and the Sword, not leſs than Fifteen Thouſand Chriſtians fell, nor was the loſs of the Infidels leſs conſiderable.</p>
            <p>The Imperialiſts having all this time blocked up <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> and fruſtrated the ſeveral attempts made to relieve it with Men, Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Ammunition, it was reſolved, That the Chriſtian Army early in the Spring, ſhould take the Field, as well to prevent the <hi>Turks,</hi> who were roving abroad in Parties, from gaining any advantage, as to draw towards that place, in order to an early Siege; of which the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa</hi> having notice, reſolved to make another attempt for its relief: yet the Undertaking was not carried on with ſuch ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but that Colonel <hi>Heuſler</hi> marching with a Party of Horſe and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, fell upon the Convoy, killed divers, and put the reſt to flight, taking Sixty Waggons laden with Proviſion and Ammunition: Yet ſome of the flyers got into the Town by an unſuſpected way; which ſo encouraged the <hi>Baſſa</hi>-Governour, that he ſent out a Party to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Countrey: And that Party falling upon <hi>Cutra,</hi> a ſmall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, put the Inhabitants to the Sword, leaving it in flames.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1685. For the Accommodation of the Army that was drawing out from divers quarters, the better to enable it to carry on the Siege, when begun, the Emperor of <hi>Germany</hi> ſent expreſs Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Cities of <hi>Ratisbone, Paſſaw, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lme,</hi> and other places upon the <hi>Danube,</hi> to provide ſtore of Proviſion, and Ammunition, with Boats, for tranſporting the Troops, as occaſion required, all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers being ordered to make their Recruits by the middle of <hi>April</hi> at fartheſt, the Eſtates of <hi>Auſtria</hi> raiſing Nine Thouſand men for the Service, at their proper charge. Nor were the <hi>Turks</hi> remiſs, but made great preparations throughout the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, it being then reported, That their Emperor would make War in his proper Perſon. For although the Chriſtians failed in their attempt upon <hi>Buda,</hi> yet a fear continued, that they might enterprize it a ſecond time; and the rather, becauſe that Garriſon was by this time much weakned, through a mortal Diſeaſe that raged there; of which <hi>Seitan,</hi> the Commanding <hi>Baſſa,</hi> and many of the prime Officers died.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were tranſacting, a Party of Four Thouſand <hi>Turks,</hi> made an Invaſion into <hi>Croatia,</hi> doing conſiderable miſchief to the Inhabitants: But being encountred by ſome Imperial Troops, and the Inhabitants, who took up Arms to oppoſe them, they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36171:6"/>were defeated with the Loſs of One Thouſand men, the reſt eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to <hi>Caniſa;</hi> to which Garriſon they appertained. And to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Injury <hi>Croatia</hi> had ſuſtained, the Garriſons of <hi>Virovitza,</hi> and <hi>Salawar,</hi> made Incurſions into the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Terri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ies, taking great Booty. And now Colonel <hi>Heuſler</hi> having notice, that another Convoy of Eight Thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> was marching toward <hi>Novigrade,</hi> to put One Hundred Waggons of Proviſion into <hi>Newhen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> he reſolved to oppoſe them, though he had with him but Two Thouſand men; and accordingly marching toward the Enemy, he attacked them in their Vanguard, killing between Three and Four Hundred upon the place, and taking a great many Priſoners. But whilſt the Diſpute laſted, thoſe that had charge of the Waggons, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired with them in great confuſion towards <hi>Novigrad,</hi> whom the Colonel thought not fit to purſue with ſo ſmall a ſtrength, for fear of being entrapped by an Ambuſcade: Yet divers of the Waggons over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing in the rough ways, were afterward taken by the Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and burnt. Nor were the <hi>Poles</hi> and <hi>Venetians</hi> leſs active on their part, to endamage the <hi>Infidels;</hi> the latter with a ſtrong power beſieging <hi>Singn;</hi> but finding that place well Garriſoned, and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, after the loſs of ſome men, they drew off: Yet the <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laques,</hi> under the protection of that Signory, falling upon the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Troops that were advancing to its Relief, cut Three or Four Hundred of them in pieces, put the reſt to flight, and took great ſpoil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caminiec,</hi> by reaſon of the Debates in the Diet of <hi>Poland,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> 1685. not being cloſely blocked up, the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon conſiſting of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> found means to roam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and ravage the Countrey, ſtoring themſelves with what Proviſions came to hand, and leading many of the poor people into miſerable Captivity. They likewiſe ſacked <hi>Radzenoaw,</hi> and ſeveral appendant Villages; which Succeſs encouraged them to make another Incurſion toward <hi>Barre</hi> and <hi>Melels<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os;</hi> but not with the like advantage: For the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> quartering in thoſe parts, taking the Allarum, fell upon them with ſuch fury, that they cut moſt of them in pieces, reſcuing the Priſoners they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and recovering all the Booty; which known to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, he, leaſt proviſion ſhould grow ſcarce, put all the <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſuch as had made no proviſion of Victuals for themſelves out of the Garriſon.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:36171:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>On the 15th. of <hi>May</hi> the great Guns and Mortars of new Invention which the Emperor had cauſed to be made, arrived at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the Troops, as well of the Circles, as of the Hereditary Countries, drew together; all Care being taken to furniſh and haſten them out, the ready Obedience and Chearfulneſs of the Commanders and Soldiers every where preſaging a ſucceſsful Campaign. And now Colonel <hi>Heuſler</hi> being ſtrengthned with additional Troops, poſted himſelf near <hi>Barkan</hi> to obſerve the motion of the Enemy, and prevent them from putting a Supply into <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> which they diligently laboured to effect; that Garriſon being then brought to ſuch Neceſſity, that Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleſh was accounted a Dainty amongſt the meaner Soldiers; and the better to ſpare Proviſion, 130 perſons were thruſt out; amongſt whom were divers Chriſtian Priſoners: And the Grand Signior, for the better Accommodation of his Army, ſent an Expreſs to <hi>Abafti,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> not only to have his Troops in readineſs to march upon the firſt Orders, but to provide one hundred thouſand meaſures of Corn, and Waggons to convey it to ſuch places as ſhould be directed. And whilſt the Dyet of <hi>Poland</hi> were coming to a Reſult for the Management of the War, a conſiderable Party of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> fell upon divers Villages in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>kraine,</hi> burnt them to the Ground, and brought away a conſiderable Booty, with many Priſoners, which did not a little trouble that King; inſomuch, that he inſtantly commanded the Troops that were in a readineſs to march to the Frontiers, himſelf reſolving, with the whole power of the Kingdom, to follow and revenge the Injury he ſuſtained by the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels; but e're he advanced, News was brought him, That the <hi>Hoſpodar Duca,</hi> Prince of <hi>Moldavia,</hi> taken Priſoner the preceding Summer, by the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> died at <hi>Leopol</hi> before the hundred thouſand Crowns which he had offered for his Ranſom, could be returned.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> in League with the Chriſtian Empire, and the other Confederate Princes having about the latter end of <hi>May</hi> joyned their Fleet with the Gallies and Men of War of the great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> it ſailed into the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> under the command of Captain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Moroſini,</hi> and there the Soldiers made divers Deſcents, taking and garriſoning ſeveral places of ſtrength, whilſt the Land-forces in <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia</hi> had the like Succeſs, which did not a little alarm the Grand Signior on that ſide: That Republick on their part vigorouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the War by Sea and Land, and not only alarmed him, but obliged him to draw off a part of thoſe Troops he deſigned for the War of <hi>Hungary,</hi> to defend his own Territories. The Inhabitants on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36171:7"/>the Sea-coaſt being moſtly inclinable to put themſelves under the Protection of the Chriſtians, or to leave the ſenceleſs Places deſolate, by retiring further into the Country, as not caring to expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Subſtance to the Miſeries of War, which, like a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, they perceived hanging over their Heads. This Succeſs of the Chriſtian Confederates in ſo many places, obliged the Cities of <hi>Eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi> and <hi>Caſchaw,</hi> to ſend their Deputies to <hi>Newſtadt,</hi> where the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Court reſided, to beg the Emperors Pardon to declare their Willingneſs to receive Imperial Garriſons, and renew their Oaths of Fidelity; nor was Count <hi>Teckely</hi> behind them in ſhew of Willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to come to an Accord with the Emperor, and tender his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; but his former Artifices on the like urgent occaſion, cauſed his Propoſals to be rejected; it being concluded, that what he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in that caſe, was only to protract time till the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army could take the Field: ſo that no Preparations were delayed on the part of the Imperialiſts, but all things haſtened for the Siege of <hi>Newheuſel.</hi> In order to which, Boats laden with Proviſion and Ammunition were ſent from <hi>Vienna</hi> and other Places, in great number. The Troops of <hi>Suabia</hi> and other Circles arrived daily; Money was given out to raiſe new Forces, and every thing carried on to the beſt Advantage; and the better to try how Count <hi>Teckely</hi> ſtood affected, General <hi>Schultz</hi> received Orders to beſiege the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngwar,</hi> the principal Fortreſs in the upper <hi>Hungary</hi> which, in hopes of being relieved by <hi>Teckely,</hi> made a reſolute Defence; he having ſent the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour private Notice that he was drawing his Troops together for that Purpoſe; which altogether confirmed the Emperor in his opinion of that Rebel's feigned Pretences; but being narrowly obſerved by the Imperial Troops in thoſe Parts, the Marqueſs <hi>Doria,</hi> Lieutenant Colonel of the Regiment of <hi>Caraffa,</hi> fell upon an advance Party of the Rebels, and put them to the Rout, taking the Commander in chief, one of <hi>Teckely</hi>'s chief Favorites.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Troops in conſiderable number, having by this time taken the Field, made divers Incurſions into <hi>Lithuania</hi> and <hi>Podolia,</hi> but met with bad Succeſs; for the Power of thoſe Provinces being in Arms, they were, for the moſt part, defeated; and the Booty they had taken, recovered; one Party more eſpecially which advanced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in twelve Miles of <hi>Leopol,</hi> was cut off by the Sieur <hi>Lizinzki,</hi> who taking the Allarm, and getting a Body of Horſe together, fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them with ſuch Fury, that thoſe who eſcaped the Sword, for the moſt part, periſhed in the Rivers, in attempting to repaſs them in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36171:7"/>places not fordable. And now there being ſome miſunderſtanding between the King of <hi>Poland</hi> and the <hi>Czars</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> which might have occaſioned a Rupture, the former, with the advice of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, reſolved to ſend an Envoy to the latter, to accommodate mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in an amicable manner, that by reaſon of any diviſion between them, the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> might have no advantage; which in the end concluded ſucceſsfully, to the ſatisfaction, advantage, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of both Nations. And the better to render the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Army more formidable, the Diet conſented to raiſe the <hi>Rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> laying great Penalties upon ſuch Gentlemen as ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs in appearing in Arms upon the firſt Summons.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chevalierd' Lanco</hi> being abroad with divers Troops (on the part of the <hi>Venetians</hi>) under his Command, met on the 29th of <hi>May,</hi> 1685. a Party of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe and Foot Marching towards <hi>Hungary,</hi> which he charged with ſuch fury, that he kill'd, and took moſt of them Priſoners, few eſcaping to tell the News; which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Mainetes</hi> more vigorouſly to proſecute the War they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took on the behalf of the Confederates againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch large Territories to defend, were forced to divide their Troops into ſo many diviſions, as rendered them the leſs able to carry on their deſigns in <hi>Hungary:</hi> Inſomuch, that divers, as well Chriſtians as others, who made their eſcape from <hi>Buda</hi> to <hi>Gran,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, That that Garriſon was in great want of all Neceſſaries: and that if it was again attacked, the <hi>Turks</hi> would not be able to defend it as formerly; but <hi>Newheuſel</hi> being the main Enterprize deſigned this Campaign, no heed was given to their Aſſeverations: yet ſo ſenſible was the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa</hi> of its weakneſs, that he ſent a part of the Proviſion thither, which was brought out of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, for the ſupply of the Army that was to act under his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which gave encouragement to the Garriſon, and ſuch as were appointed thereto to go on with their Fortifications ruined the laſt Summer. And now the Seige of <hi>Newheuſel</hi> being reſolved, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Bonviſo,</hi> the <hi>Pope's Nuncio,</hi> at the Imperial Court, gave One Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thouſand Florins toward the Expences of the <hi>Blockade,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing a greater ſum for the Encouragement of the Officers and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers when it ſhould be taken. Whereupon on the Eleventh of <hi>June,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> took his leave of the Court, and dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rted for <hi>Hungary,</hi> with full power to act with the Imperial Forces this Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign, as he ſhall judg moſt advantageous for the Service of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36171:8"/>
            <p>General <hi>Schultz,</hi> notwithſtanding his having taken the Baſe-Town, or Out-Fortreſs of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngwar,</hi> and defeated a Party ſent out by Count <hi>Teckeley</hi> to ſuccour it: Yet the Upper Town being ſtrongly fortified, ſtored with Proviſion and Ammunition, after ſome Loſs before it, he thought fit to draw off, and wait a more favourable opportunity to attack it.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were tranſacting, Ten Thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> found means to paſs the Bridg of <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and joyn that Body of an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my they had formed near <hi>Belgrade,</hi> there giving out, that they would relieve <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> whatever it coſt them. And the better to enable them to make an attempt for its relief, the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Boſſina</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Orders from the <hi>Port</hi> to march with the Troops of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try towards <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the 13th of <hi>June</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with a great Train of Officers and Nobility, arrived at the Imperial Camp, near <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> where he found things in a great forwardneſs; and the ſame day held a Council of War: after which Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> with Four Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe, was ſent out to learn the poſture of the Enemy: And in the mean while the Troops of <hi>Bavaria, Cologne, Lunenburg, Franco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Suabia,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Rhine,</hi> were expected to make up the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Fifty Thouſand Fighting men, beſides other Troops raiſed by the Confederate Princes, which were upon their March, and ſuch as were poſted in divers places, to preſerve the Provinces from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſion of the Enemy. And although General <hi>Schultz</hi> at preſent failed to reduce <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngwar,</hi> by reaſon his Correſpondence with ſome of the Garriſon was diſcovered; yet he had the good fortune to take the Town of <hi>Onoth,</hi> a place poſſeſſed by the Rebels, with the loſs of Twenty Two Men only on his part; where he found a great Booty, conſiſting of 300 Horſes, and 1000 Head of Cattle, killing 130 of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Caprara,</hi> who was ſent out to obſerve the motion of the Enemy, defeated a Party of <hi>Turks</hi> that were on their March to <hi>Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grad,</hi> making his Report, That the <hi>Turks</hi> near <hi>Buda</hi> were Forty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtrong; which he learned from ſuch Priſoners as he had taken in the Action. Whereupon the Vice-Roy of <hi>Croatia</hi> received an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs to draw his Troops into the Field, the better to be in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to prevent any Incurſion that might be made into that Province. The <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> the <hi>Count D'Eſterhaſi,</hi> made likewiſe what ſpeed he could to raiſe the Eight Thouſand <hi>Hungarians</hi> he propoſed to bring into the Emperor's Service, to act conjunctly with the Army, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36171:8"/>ſeparately, as his Imperial Majeſty ſhould think moſt convenient for his advantage; the Principal Officers of the Imperial Army being in their order theſe:</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> General; Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> Commander of the Foot, as <hi>Mareſchal De Camp,</hi> General; and under him the Duke <hi>De Croy,</hi> General of the Artilery; the Prince of <hi>Newburg,</hi> Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the <hi>Teutonick Order;</hi> the Count <hi>De Souches,</hi> and <hi>Count de Scherf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenburg,</hi> the two latter in quality of Major-Generals; the <hi>Count De Caprara,</hi> Commander of the Horſe, as <hi>Mareſchal De Camp</hi> General; under him Prince <hi>Louis</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> and the <hi>Count De Dunewaldet,</hi> as Generals of Horſe; the <hi>Count De Palfie,</hi> Lieutenant General; <hi>Count Taff,</hi> the <hi>Baron de Mercy,</hi> the <hi>Count de Lodron,</hi> and the <hi>Count De Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> Major Generals; the Prince <hi>de Solms,</hi> Commander of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry in <hi>Croatia,</hi> and the <hi>Marqueſs de Lavergne,</hi> of the Infantry under General <hi>Leſlie.</hi> The Forces againſt the Rebels in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungary,</hi> are commanded by General <hi>Schultz;</hi> and the Count <hi>Eſterhaſi</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thoſe <hi>Hungarians</hi> he raiſes for the Service.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> though he was not ignorant that the Chriſtians intended to open the Campaign with the Siege of <hi>Newheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> the place which he had an Expreſs from the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve at the hazard of all his Forces; yet he ſtayed near <hi>Belgrade,</hi> to expect the <hi>Aſian</hi> Troops, which were on their March; whoſe neglect in advancing, brought ſuch a fear upon <hi>Novigrad,</hi> that although it had been re-inforced with three Hundred <hi>Janizaries,</hi> yet upon the approach of <hi>Count Caprara,</hi> with Three Thouſand Horſe, the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon left the Town, and betook them to the Caſtle, as imagining him to be the Vant-guard of the Chriſtian Army; and the rather, for that it was ſome time given out, That that place would be firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged.</p>
            <p>A Party of <hi>Huſſars,</hi> in the ſervice of the Emperor, being abroad, fell upon Two Hundred <hi>Janizaries</hi> near <hi>Buda,</hi> put them to the rout, killed moſt of them, and took the <hi>Aga</hi> that commanded them, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner; about whom Letters were found from the <hi>Vizier</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> to the Baſſa of <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> wherein he exhorted him, in caſe he was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked, to defend the place to the laſt Extremity, and not deſpair of being relieved. General <hi>Schultz</hi> purſuing his ſucceſs in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungary,</hi> made himſelf Maſter of the Fortreſs of <hi>Caſnahauka,</hi> and moſt of the <hi>Hungarians</hi> of that place, upon their ſupplication, were taken into the Emperor's ſervice.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:36171:9"/>
            <p>A Party of Eight Thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> having about the beginning of <hi>June</hi> beſieged the Fortreſs of <hi>Duare</hi> in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> ſcituate between <hi>Spalatro</hi> and <hi>Cataro,</hi> the <hi>Proveditor,</hi> General <hi>Valier,</hi> and <hi>Signior Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieli,</hi> Commiſſary-General of the Horſ, drew together the Forces of the Signory under their Command, and attacked the <hi>Infidels</hi> in three places, with ſuch vigor and ſucceſs, that they forced them to raiſe the Siege, and retire in great diſorder, leaving behind them Three pieces of Cannon, Three Mortars, a Petard, Fourteen Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and the greateſt part of their Baggage, together with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of Proviſion, newly arrived in their Camp. Three Hundred were killed upon the place, Eighty taken Priſoners, and the <hi>Marlaques</hi> ſent out in the purſuit of the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, who put them moſtly to the Sword. Of the <hi>Venetians</hi> only Ten were killed, and Thirty wounded. The <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Boſſina,</hi> who by this time had his Orders for marching into <hi>Hungary,</hi> was countermanded, being upon the Borders with Four Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Horſe; and underſtanding the Leaguers were attacked, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to their relief with all diligence: but coming too late, was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf charged by the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and put to the rout. Whereupon many of the neighbouring Inhabitants caſting off the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Yoak, put themſelves under the protection of the Chriſtiands; and upon their humble ſupplication, had Quarters aſſigned them by the <hi>Provedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Valier;</hi> which obliged the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> to haſten his Troops out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> compelling the Merchants Ships at <hi>Smirna,</hi> and other Ports, to tranſport them. And by reaſon ſome of the <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s upon their arrival at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> had not compleated their Levies, he cauſed them to be ſtrangled.</p>
            <p>On the 23d of <hi>June,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with a detachment of 700 Horſe, and two Companies of <hi>Huſſars,</hi> marched towards <hi>Gran,</hi> to obſerve by what way the place might be beſt relieved, in caſe the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhould, to divert the Imperial Forces, beſiege it. And the 25th of <hi>June</hi> his Highneſs paſſed the River <hi>Gran</hi> over a Bridg of Boats, with Three Thouſand Horſe, Two Hundred Dragoons, and a party of <hi>Huſſars,</hi> to obſerve the ſcituation of <hi>Novigrad.</hi> The next day he came before the place, at what time the <hi>Baſſa</hi> Governour ſent out Three Hundred Horſe in Two Squadrons, who skirmiſhed with the <hi>Huſſars,</hi> and a detachment of Foot, to ſecure the Retreat of the Horſe; which obliged the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to ſend a detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to poſſeſs the Hills, from whence the place might be the better obſerved; and went thither in perſon, when the Troops command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Princes <hi>De Conti</hi> and <hi>De-la-Roche Sur-Yon,</hi> advanced to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36171:9"/>Foot of the Rampart, notwithſtanding the continual Fire of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Infantry, which were poſted there. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken a view of the place, commanded the Troops that kept the Hills, to retire; who in their Retreat had a brisk skirmiſh with the Enemy's Horſe: But the Princes <hi>De Conti</hi> and <hi>De la Roche Sur-yon,</hi> advancing to their aſſiſtance, the <hi>Turks</hi> retired in much diſorder. In this action the <hi>Chevalier de' Poncherron,</hi> received a ſhot in the Breaſt; and ſeveral others were wounded. On the 4th of <hi>July</hi> his Highneſs returned to the Army before <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> and gave ſuch encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Pioniers,</hi> that they carried on the Works with much bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, notwithſtanding the Fire of the Enemy: ſo that by the 8th of <hi>July</hi> the Lines were finiſhed: And on the 10th, as the Chriſtians were raiſing a Battery, the <hi>Turks</hi> made a Sally, to hinder their work; but were ſoon obliged to retire in great diſorder: Yet in the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prince <hi>De Commercy,</hi> Prince <hi>Ferdinand de Wirtemberg,</hi> and ſome other perſons of Quality, who were Voluntiers, were wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. On the 11th at night the Trenches were opened, and the <hi>Baron de Beck</hi> poſted himſelf within Piſtol-ſhot of the <hi>Covert-way,</hi> and maintained himſelf there notwithſtanding the continual Fire of the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſieged. And about Nine of the Clock in the Evening Three Thouſand Foot opened the Trenches on the other ſide the River, within Eighty paces of the Ditch. On the 12th, the Trench was carried from the right to the left; and the Imperialiſts began to raiſe Two Batteries, to ruin the Defences of the place. The 13th at night they finiſhed the work, and made a Re-doubt at the Head of each Trench, to defend themſelves againſt the Enemies Sallies. The 14th at night they began a falſe attack on the ſide oppoſite to the true one, and made a parallel which joyned the Heads of the Two Trenches. On the 15th at night, they carried on the Two Attacks to the Edg of the Ditch, and finiſhed a Battery of Eighteen pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Cannon, in the middle of the Parallel. On the 16th, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen day, a Chriſtian Slave, though with Chains on his Legs, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to eſcape out of the Town; but Three <hi>Turks</hi> purſued him, and cut off his Head: Yet ere they could retire, Two of them were killed by the Shot of the Imperialiſts. On the 16th at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, the beſieged made a continual fire, and ſhot a great many Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ows and Stones; by which means Fifteen Chriſtians were killed, and Thirty wounded. On the 17th the Enemy abandoned a Phlanque wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch covered one of the Gates of the place on the left of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack; and at the ſame time ſet fire on that ſide to the <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſedes;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36171:10"/>upon which there were Three or Four Hundred Heads of Chriſtians. As for this place, it is ſcituate upon a Plain full of <hi>Moors,</hi> but in moſt places paſſable, having Six <hi>Baſtions</hi> lined with Stone-work, a Ditch full of water, between Seven and Eight Foot deep, and Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Foot broad: But for Out-works, it has only Two Half Moons before the Two Gates, and the River <hi>Neutra:</hi> And in the Town, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the arrival of the Imperial Army, were ſuppoſed between 1000 and 1200 fighting men.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Siege of <hi>Newheuſel</hi> went on thus ſucceſsfully, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Bavaria</hi> arrived with a ſplendid Train at <hi>Vienna;</hi> where at his landing he was received by the Emperor, and the Cannon of the City fired in token of his welcom; the Garriſon-Soldiers and Burghers being likewiſe in Arms. Whereupon his Imperial Majeſty and Electoral Highneſs went to the <hi>Auguſtins-Church;</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the young <hi>Arch-Dutcheſs</hi> was ſoon ofter brought by the Empreſs, and the Empreſs <hi>Dowager,</hi> and there Married to his Electoral Highneſs of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> by the Biſhop of <hi>Colonitz:</hi> which done, the Cannon round the City was again diſcharged, and their Highneſſes were conducted to the Pallace, where they ſupped publickly with their Imperial Majeſties (the Ambaſſadors of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> ſitting at the ſame Table). During Supper the Cannon was diſcharged a third time, and the Pallace, and almoſt all the Houſes in the City were illuminated with Flambeaux and Torches, accompanied with all other Expreſſions of Joy: In which we will leave them, and return to the Camp before <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> where his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſoon after arrived.</p>
            <p>On the 18th and 19th of <hi>July</hi> nothing conſiderable paſſed: but on the 20th, the Imperialiſts battered the Wall with Nine pieces of Cannon, and caſt <hi>Bombs</hi> and <hi>Carcaſes</hi> into the Town, which greatly endamaged, and annoyed the beſieged. The night following they lodged themſelves on the right and left, in the Ditch: And though it was a very dangerous work, yet only a Captain of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Metternich,</hi> and an other of the Troops of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> were killed, and Three or Four Soldiers wounded. The ſame night they finiſhed the Lines of Communication along the Ditch, from one Battery to the other; and the Imperial Dragoons, together with thoſe of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> making about Five Thouſand Men, were ſent under the Command of the Count of <hi>Stirum,</hi> towards <hi>Commora,</hi> to cover the Two Bridges the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had caus'd to be laid over the <hi>Danube.</hi> The 21ſt the Beſiegers fired on the Town with great
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36171:10"/>Fury; continuing to do ſo all that night, from a Battery of Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen pieces of Cannon, and from Two of Twelve pieces; as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from Fourteen Mortar-pieces, which ſet fire to divers Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: but the diligence of the Inhabitants was ſo great, that they preſently extinguiſhed the flame. That night they raiſed Two new Batteries of Six Pieces of Cannon, each very near the Ditch; and a Thouſand men were commanded to work near the <hi>Gran-Gate,</hi> in order to let the water into the River <hi>Neutra,</hi> which is Five Foot lower than the Ditch. The ſame work was alſo begun on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the Town; yet in the carrying it on only Four men were killed, and Four and Twenty wounded. The 22d the Beſiegers renewed the fire of their Mortars and Cannon; which continued with ſuch ſucceſs, that the Town ſeemed all on a flame for the ſpace of Four and Twenty Hours. On the ſame day, and on the 23d the <hi>Turks</hi> brought a great many Chriſtian Slaves in Chains, to repair the Ramparts the Cannon had ruined; as likewiſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the Compaſſion of the Imperialiſts, that they might forbear fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> wrote a Letter to the <hi>Baſſa</hi> Governour, letting him underſtand, That if he did miſuſe thoſe Slaves, he would not give any Quarter to the Garriſon, in caſe the place was taken: to which no anſwer was returned. The 23d at night a Trench was cut into the Ditch, for the paſſage of Two co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Boats, to make with Planks and Rafters a Lodgment for the <hi>Miners</hi> at the foot of the <hi>Baſtion;</hi> but one of thoſe Boats preſently ſunk, the other meeting with little better ſucceſs, the Lieutenant of the <hi>Miners</hi> being wounded, the beſiegers were forced to quit that Enterprize. And the Prince <hi>De Conti</hi> coming out of the Trenches, was lightly wounded with a Muſquet-Bullet in the Head. The 24th the beſieged made a Sally, and ſurpriſed ſome of the Troops of <hi>Suabia</hi> in a Redoubt they had made before the Tower of <hi>Vienna,</hi> of whom Three Hundred, with a Lieutenant Colonel, and Captain, were killed. On the 25th the Chriſtians finiſhed Two Batteries on the Ditch, and began to fill it; and the ſame day had an Hundred men killed and wounded, the <hi>Sieur Roſs,</hi> Colonel of the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Troops, being of the number of the firſt. The ſame day a Barrel of Powder took fire, by which Five and Twenty men were killed and wounded; and Collonel <hi>Heuſler</hi> and Colonel <hi>Zabor,</hi> who were ſent out to obſerve the Enemy, came back, having cut off a Party. of about Thirty <hi>Turks,</hi> near <hi>Gran,</hi> and taken ſeveral Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, giving the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> an account, That the <hi>Ottoman</hi> At<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36171:11"/>commanded by the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> was marching towards <hi>Gran;</hi> and that there were Twelve Hundred <hi>Tartars</hi> near <hi>Novigrad,</hi> in a readineſs to joyn them. And at the ſame inſtant Prince <hi>Waldeck</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the Camp. On the <hi>25th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> the beſieged began to fill the Ditch; the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> and the other General Officers being the greateſt part of the night in the Trenches, which they continued to do the night following. On the <hi>27th</hi> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged ſallied, and ruined part of the Beſiegers work, made for let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the water out of the Ditch. The reſt of the night, and the day following, the <hi>Bavarians</hi> were imployed in raiſing a Re-doubt at the Head of their work, to cover it againſt the Enemies Sally. The <hi>28th</hi> the Beſiegers carried their Gallery very near to the Walls of the Town; but the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſieged, with their Granado's, and other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Fireworks, burnt a part of it, which was repaired on the <hi>29th.</hi> On the <hi>30th</hi> the beſieged made another Sally, ſuppoſing to ruin the Gallery, to which they had ſet fire; inſomuch that the flame ſeized on one of the Batteries: whereupon the Chriſtians that were in the Trenches, retired in ſome diſorder. But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> haſtning thither, with his drawn Sword, and threatning to kill thoſe that were running away, he himſelf carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back the Officers to the Poſts they had quitted; and directing and encouraging the Soldiers, the fire was put out. On this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion his Highneſs was a long time expoſed to the Fire of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and Nine or Ten perſons killed very near him. The <hi>30th</hi> and <hi>31ſt</hi> the Beſiegers repaired the Gallery, and carried it to the Wall of the Town, in deſpite of the Enemies firing from their Works; and with their Cannon ſo ruined the <hi>Attack-Baſtion,</hi> that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my could no longer make uſe of the Cannon they had there: and the breaches were likewiſe very much enlarged in the Curtain. On the Firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the beſieged made a Sally with Four Hundred men; but were repulſed at the coſt of Forty Chriſtians Lives; the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Souches</hi> in that Action being wounded in the Neck with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Siege of <hi>Newheuſel</hi> was vigorouſly carried on, News came to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> That on the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> the <hi>Seraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier</hi> ſat down before <hi>Gran,</hi> notwithſtanding Five Hundred Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts the day before were gotten into it; and that the <hi>Turks</hi> had in a manner encompaſſed it; opening the <hi>31ſt</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Trench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and raiſing Batteries upon the adjacent Hills, commanding the Town called St. <hi>George</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas.</hi> Whereupon the Duke of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36171:11"/>
               <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> leaving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Sixteen and Seventeen Thouſand men to maintain the Siege, under the Command of Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Croy,</hi> on the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>Augu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> marched with the reſt of the Army, either to fight the <hi>Seraſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> or oblige him to retire from before <hi>Gran;</hi> the whole Army at that time conſiſting of Twelve Thouſand Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Horſe, and Ten Thouſand Foot; Two Thouſand <hi>Bavarian</hi> Horſe, and Six Thouſand Foot; Twelve Thouſand <hi>Lunenburghers</hi> Horſe and Foot; Six Thouſand Horſe and Foot of the Elector of <hi>Cologn</hi>'s Forces; and Three Thouſand Five Hundred of <hi>Franco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> in all about One and Fifty Thouſand. The beſieged, upon drawing off the greateſt part of the Imperial Army, imagining that the Chriſtians were about to raiſe the Siege, expreſſed much Joy with Muſick and Acclamations; but were ſoon made ſenſible of their miſtake, by the Volleys of ſmall ſhot, and thundring of the Cannons, which made the Commanding <hi>Baſſa</hi> offer to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the place, in caſe he might march out with the Garriſon with their Arms, Baggage, and all the Cannon; with Drums beating, and Colours flying: but the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> would not hearken to theſe Conditions. The Second of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the beſieged came into the Ditch in two ſmall Boats; but found there ſo good a Guard, that they were forced to retire without attempting any thing. On the Third day the Chriſtians ſounded the Ditch, and found there was between Four and Five Foot water: And the night following they raiſed a Battery of Twenty Pieces of Cannon on the Edg of the Ditch; and Collonel <hi>Bourgſdorff,</hi> Governour of <hi>Duſſeldorff,</hi> who arrived in the Camp the day before, was killed with a Muſquet-ſhot. The Fourth the Chriſtians began to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſide of the Attack of the Troops of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> but the <hi>Turks</hi> very much hindred their Work with their Cannon and Small Shot: However it was continued and carried to the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Line of Communication, over-againſt the Curtain, and a new Battery raiſed of Four Mortars. The Fifth the Enemy made ſo great a Fire from the new Battery they had raiſed in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Curtain, that the Chriſtians who carried on the work, were put into ſome diſorder, and a part of the Gallery ruined; as likewiſe many men killed and wounded, who were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently covered: ſo that the reſt were obliged to diſcontinue the work till night. The <hi>7th,</hi> being the day whereon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> &amp;c. drew off, as aforeſaid, for the Relief of <hi>Gran,</hi> by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36171:12"/>the conſent of the Emperor, to whom he had ſent an Expreſs to acquaint him with his Reſolutions; the Attacks were ſtrongly carried on, and the next day the Cannon from the Batteries play'd with ſuch fury, that moſt of the Enemies Cannon was diſmount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In which proſperous progreſs we will leave the Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> and follow the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with the other part of the Chriſtian Army.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa</hi> beſieging <hi>Gran</hi> with an Army of about Forty Thouſand men, having raiſed, as aforeſaid, his Batteries on the Hills of <hi>St. George</hi> and <hi>St. Thomas,</hi> ſeveral pieces of his Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non were diſmounted by the Cannon of the beſieged from the Caſtle: Yet on the Firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> he cauſed his Trenches to be advanced: And on the Second the beſieged, to hinder it, made a furious Sally, in which they killed about Two Hundred <hi>Turks.</hi> On the Third, the <hi>Turks</hi> attacked the lower Town, but were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed with the loſs of Three Hundred men, who were killed upon the place, and ſeveral Priſoners taken: when in the mean time the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having held a Council of War, it was reſolved to march with the Army to fight the Enemy, leaving Sixteen or Seventeen Thouſand men to make good the Siege of <hi>Newheuſel.</hi> And the Count <hi>De Lamberg</hi> was ſent to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to acquaint him with the Reſolution that was taken; which the Emperor highly approving, the Count was ſent back to the Duke, with Orders to purſue the ſame, who upon his Return, found all things were diſpoſed for the March: but becauſe a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Enemy was poſted at <hi>Novigrad,</hi> with a deſign when the Army had paſſed the <hi>Danube,</hi> to attempt the Relief of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heuſel,</hi> his Highneſs cauſed ſeveral Retrenchments to be made for the ſecurity of the Camp, and defer'd his March till they were finiſhed (which being done, on the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> he ſet forward, and paſſing the <hi>Danube,</hi> advanced towards <hi>Gran,</hi> with a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to fight the Enemy. But upon the approach of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Army, they quitted the Siege of <hi>Gran,</hi> and drew up in <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia</hi> behind a <hi>Moraſs,</hi> which could not be paſſed but by Deffiles, or Lanes; as likewiſe poſſeſſing Two Hills of difficult acceſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Plain by which the Chriſtians muſt march to them; their Right Wing extending almoſt to the <hi>Danube,</hi> and their Left to a great Wood which covered the Flank. Whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> drew up his Army in <hi>Battalia</hi> on the Plain, the moſt advantageouſly the Ground would permit; and in that poſture
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36171:12"/>both Armies faced each other for the ſpace of Three days. When on the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at night, a <hi>Renegado Polander</hi> making his Eſcape from the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, came into the Chriſtian Camp, and informed the Duke, That the <hi>Seraſquier</hi> having received an account, That the Chriſtian Army was but Twenty Thouſand ſtrong, he reſolved to attack them. His Highneſs thereupon, and to confirm the Enemy in their Opinion of the weakneſs of the Chriſtians, and to engage them to a Fight upon more equal ground, retreated with the whole Army about an hours March towards <hi>Commorra;</hi> which the <hi>Turks</hi> perceiving the next morning, and that there was a ſufficient Interval between the <hi>Moraſs</hi> and the Rear of the Chriſtian Army, to draw up in <hi>Battalia,</hi> they paſſed the Deffiles; and having again formed themſelves, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced towards the Chriſtians with their uſual ſhouts and crys, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Right Wing, commanded by the Elector of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> and Prince <hi>Waldeck,</hi> who received them with that Bravery, Courage, and Firmneſs, that they did not long keep their ground. At the ſame time their Right Wing attacked the Left Wing of the Chriſtians, and endeavoured to have fallen upon their Flank; but with as bad ſucceſs as the other, being beaten off with much bravery. When being thus repulſed, and finding they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the account they had of the Chriſtians ſtength, they began to fall into great diſorder; which was very much increaſed by the diſcharge of Thirty pieces of Cannon, laden with ſmall ſhot, that upon the opening of the Chriſtian Troops were fired upon them, and made a great ſlaughter; which ſo terrified them, that upon the Second diſcharge they betook themſelves to flight, being purſued by the Firſt Line of the Chriſtians, and a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of Voluntiers, who gave in this occaſion great proof of their Courage. So that the <hi>Turks</hi> re-paſſing the <hi>Deffiles</hi> in great confuſion, were charged upon with ſuch Fury, that a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſlaughter enſued: All that oppoſed were cut in pieces; and the Chriſtians purſuing their Victory, entred their Camp, making themſelves Maſters of it; the <hi>Turks</hi> flying for ſafety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Buda;</hi> and after them were ſent the <hi>Hungarians</hi> and <hi>Croats,</hi> with a detachment of <hi>Cuiraſſiers,</hi> commanded by the Baron <hi>De Mercy,</hi> the Count <hi>De Stirum,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Heuſler,</hi> who cut off divers of the Rear. As for their Tents, Baggage and Artillery, the latter conſiſting of Three and Twenty Pieces of Cannon, and Four Mortars; all that they had there; they having left the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36171:13"/>reſt before <hi>Gran,</hi> they were taken by the Chriſtians, 4000 <hi>Janizaries</hi> ſlain, and 2000 <hi>Spahies,</hi> beſides 3000 that were computed to be killed at the Siege of <hi>Gran,</hi> with only the loſs of a hundred Chriſtians, not one Perſon of note killed or wounded, except the Sieur <hi>Van Dingen,</hi> General of the Battalia of the Troops of <hi>Franconia,</hi> who was wounded in the Shoulder; and the better to encourage the Purſuers, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ordered, That whatever they took in the Purſuit, ſhould fall to their own ſhares.</p>
            <p>After this Defeat of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army, his Highneſs marched back towards <hi>Newheuſel</hi> in order to finiſh that Siege, but met the welcome News of its being taken; and a while after that, the <hi>Turks</hi> of <hi>Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grad,</hi> an important place between <hi>Barkin</hi> and <hi>Peſt,</hi> had demoliſhed and deſerted it upon their Magazines being fired with Lightning; which blowing up, beat down a great part of the Wall of the Town, and ruined the principal Baſtion; whereupon he ſent Colonel <hi>Heuſler</hi> with 1500 Men to obſerve the place; who coming thither, found the <hi>Turks</hi> had quite abandoned it, and that they had nailed up what Cannon they were not capable of conveying thence; whereupon he left 200 Men in it, and returned with the reſt to give his Highneſs an account in what Poſture he found it: Whereupon 200 more were ſent thither. Yet whilſt the <hi>Turks</hi> beſieged <hi>Gran,</hi> the Seraſquier Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa had ſent out 12000 Men to beſiege <hi>Vicegrade,</hi> a ſmall Imperial Garriſon, conſiſting of no more than 300 Chriſtians; but they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it with great Bravery, till 40 of them were killed, and 30 wounded. At what time perceiving the Miners were at work, and a great Breach made in the Wall, they capitulated to march out with Bag and Baggage to the <hi>Danube,</hi> where they embarked, and were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by Water to the Imperial Camp: After which, the <hi>Turks</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed the place. But to return to <hi>Newheuſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the abſence of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Count <hi>de Eſterhaſi</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving in the Camp before <hi>Newheuſel</hi> with 4000 <hi>Hungarians,</hi> left 2000 there, and with the other two thouſand marched towards <hi>Gran,</hi> to joyn that part of the Army; which freſh Supply ſo encouraged the Beſiegers, that having ruined the Baſtions of the beſieged, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted almoſt all their Cannon, a general Storm was reſolved upon, and carryed on with ſuch Succeſs on the 19th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> that in a ſhort time the Beſiegers lodged themſelves upon one of the attackt Baſtions; upon which the beſieged placed three white Flags on the Retrenchment they had made within the Baſtion, and deſired to capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate, which was refuſed by the Beſiegers, who, advancing, made
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36171:13"/>themſelves Maſters of that Retrenchment, and entred the Town, where they met with no oppoſition; the <hi>Turks</hi> endeavouring to ſave themſelves in their Houſes, but were all that were met in the firſt heat put to the Sword; 300 <hi>Turks</hi> ſeeing the place loſt, retired into a Baſtion, and from thence threw themſelves, into the Ditch, where they were either drowned, or put to the Sword; ſo that of the whole Garriſon very few eſcaped. The Baſſa, a Renegado <hi>Bohemian,</hi> was wounded and made Priſoner, but ſometime after died of his Wounds. A great number of Chriſtian Slaves were releaſed from their miſerable Bondage, and the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Officers, to whom Quarters were given, caſt into <hi>Durance.</hi> In the place were found 80 braſs Cannon, all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted; 10 Mortars, 8 of which were likewiſe diſmounted; forty thouſand weight of Powder; ſo that with little loſs, in conſideration of the great and ſignal Succeſs on the part of the Chriſtians, on the 15th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Army was defeated, and <hi>Newheuſel</hi> reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, which coſt the <hi>Turks</hi> ſo dear in taking; on the 19th of the ſame Month, 1685. upon which <hi>Vaccia</hi> and divers other places were abandoned by the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were tranſacted in <hi>Hungary,</hi> General <hi>Mohila,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> fell upon 10000 <hi>Tartars,</hi> who had poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves near <hi>Ratiskaw,</hi> killing a great number of them, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reſt to flight; ſo that in great diſorder they repaſſed the <hi>Nic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> and thereupon ſent his aſſurance to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> that he would ever remain faithful to him. The Baſſa of <hi>Boſſina,</hi> again attempting to beſiege <hi>Dunare</hi> in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> to repair his Honour, was, upon the Approach of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Troops, obliged to retire in great Diſorder. And the <hi>Venetian</hi> Fleet joyned with the Gallies of the Pope, the great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> being abroad in the <hi>Levant,</hi> Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>Molino</hi> with 30 Men of War, and 5 Galeaſſes was ſent to cruiſe in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> where he fell in with, and defeated a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy, compoſed of a great number of Saiquers laden with Proviſions and Ammunition, going to <hi>Theſſalonic,</hi> taking fourteen, and ſinking moſt of the remainder; and at the ſame time the <hi>Venetians</hi> attacked <hi>Coron,</hi> advancing to the Body of that Town, battering it with ſeven pieces of Cannon, and as many Mortars, with which they ruined a great part of it, laying open a large Breach in the Wall; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Baſſa Governour put up a white Flag, and deſired to capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, but Captain General <hi>Moroſini,</hi> Commander of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> let him underſtand, that he expected to have the place ſurrendred upon Diſcretion; which put the Baſſa into ſuch a Rage, that he immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36171:14"/>cauſed a black Flag to be put up in its ſtead, ſignifying thereby his Reſolution to defend it to the laſt; of whoſe Diſtreſs the Baſſa of <hi>Petraſſo</hi> having notice, drew together between 7 and 8000 Men, with which he marched to relieve the place; but on his way underſtanding the Strength of the Beſiegers, he durſt not attempt it, but contented himſelf with ſending ſome Troops to re-inforce the Garriſon of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and with falling upon the <hi>Greeks</hi> in that Neighbourhood, of whom he made a great ſlaughter, and afterwards poſſeſſed himſelf of <hi>Larini,</hi> a ſmall place near <hi>Corinth.</hi> Whereupon the Siege of <hi>Coron,</hi> the principal City of <hi>Morea,</hi> was carried on with ſuch Succeſs, that upon a general Storm the beſieged were beaten from their Defences, and the Beſiegers entred with ſuch Fury, that ere the heat was allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 3000 <hi>Turks,</hi> together with their Baſſa, were put to the Sword, and on the part of the <hi>Venetians</hi> only 400 killed; amongſt which were two Knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> and Prince <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Courbon,</hi> the Marqueſs <hi>de St. Paule,</hi> with about thirty Knights of <hi>Malta,</hi> and ſome other perſons of Quality were wounded. In the City were found 76 Pieces of Braſs Cannon, with a great Quantity of Amunition and Proviſion. The Plunder of this Place was reckoned to amount to the value of two Millions of Livers: And beſide the taking this Place, they defeated a great Body of <hi>Turks</hi> under the leading of <hi>Kallil,</hi> Vizier Baſſa of <hi>Morea,</hi> killing above a thouſand of them, together with the ſaid Baſſa, putting the reſt to Flight, and poſſeſſing themſelves of great Booty, beſides nine Pieces of Cannon and two Mortars: Whereupon 300 <hi>Maynotes</hi> put themſelves into the Service of the Republick, aſſuring the Captain General, That many more of their Aſſociates would caſt off the <hi>Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Yoke, and follow their Example. The City of <hi>Eſperies,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the feigned or pretended Submiſſion, being encouraged by Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> refuſing to open its Gates to the Imperial Forces, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Schultz,</hi> with the Forces under his Command, on the 20th of <hi>July</hi> came before it, having a good Train of Artillery, and the next day cauſed the Trenches to be opened, and carried, with the loſs of one Man, near to the Ditch of the Town; at what time the place had in it a thouſand Men in Garriſon, not accounting the Burghers; and the ſame Night finiſhed two Batteries, from which he played upon the beſieged with great Fury, and they as reſolutely fired upon the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts; whereupon three ſeveral Aſſaults were made with conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Loſs on both ſides.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36171:14"/>
            <p>Whilſt this Slege laſted, General <hi>Leſlie</hi> having left his Cannon at <hi>Virovitza,</hi> marched the 9th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> with a Body of 6000 Men, and on the 10th came to <hi>Mouſtaroima,</hi> and in the Evening detach'd an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer with 500 <hi>Croats</hi> and ſome Foot to inveſt <hi>Michalowitz,</hi> in which was a Garriſon of 60 Men, who immediately ſurrendered it upon Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion, and the General put a Garriſon of 200 into it. In the mean time the <hi>Turks</hi> made ſeveral ſignals from the Caſtles they have upon the <hi>Drave,</hi> and ſent out Parties to give the Alarm to thoſe of <hi>Eſſeck.</hi> On the 12 he continued his March towards <hi>Caraſſina;</hi> at what time the Baſſa of <hi>Eſſeck</hi> advanced with 600 Horſe, and charged his Vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard, but was beaten back, and forced to retire in great Confuſion, with conſiderable Loſs; when on the part of the Imperialiſts, a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and 26 Soldiers only were killed. On the 13th he marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> and being come into the great Plain not far from that place, he perceived a Body of 1000 <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe; their Foot, whoſe number the Chriſtians could not exactly obſerve, being poſted near the Town; upon which the General having drawn up his Forces in Battalia, commanded the <hi>Croats</hi> of the two Wings to advance and charge the Enemy; which they did with ſo much Reſolution and Bravery, that the <hi>Turks</hi> ſoon fell into diſorder, and in the end to plain Flight. Their Foot at the ſame time making what haſte they could into the Town and Caſtle. Whereupon General <hi>Leſlie</hi> gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Troops to attack the Town; which they performed with ſuch Courage, that ſcaling the Walls, with their Swords in their Hands, the <hi>Turks</hi> endeavoured to ſave themſelves, with their Wives and Children, by Water; and ſome by getting into the Caſtle; and of the former, many were taken in little Boats. As for this Town, it is large, there being in it about 500 Shops of ſeveral Trades, and two great Markets, which were then filled with great quantities of Rice, Corn, and other Proviſions. The Pillage of which Town Count <hi>Leſlie</hi> gave to the Soldiers; and having poſted Guards to ſecure the Avenues, he went to view the Bridge which is 8000 paces in length on the other ſide the <hi>Drave,</hi> and 1100 on this ſide, being 12 paces broad, over which the <hi>Turks</hi> make their greateſt Paſſage into <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> and there he found, that thoſe who fled, had broken down a part on the other ſide of the River, to hinder the Chriſtians from purſuing them; and that it would be very difficult to burn what was beyond that Breach. Whereupon he contented himſelf with burning that part on this ſide the <hi>Drave,</hi> which was ſoon deſtroyed with Fire; and 20 Soldiers ſwam the River, with a Reſolution to ſet Fire on ſeveral
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36171:15"/>Mills on the other ſide; but upon the appearance of ſeveral <hi>Turks</hi> on the Banks, they thought convenient to return without effecting it. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Succeſs, the <hi>Croats</hi> deſired General <hi>Leſlie</hi> to give them leave to attack the Caſtle, to which he conſented; but finding it more ſtrongly fortified than they imagined, were obliged to quit their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, after the loſs of 50 of their Number; and on the 15th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> General <hi>Leſlie</hi> marched back towards <hi>Michalowitz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time the Governour of <hi>Carelſtadt,</hi> the Count <hi>de Herberſtein</hi> having concerted with the Chevalier <hi>Janco,</hi> General of the <hi>Morlaques,</hi> who had put themſelves under the Protection of the <hi>Venetians</hi> to invade the Province of <hi>Corbavia;</hi> and that at the ſame time the <hi>Morlaques</hi> ſhould make an Incurſion into the Province of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea,</hi> he marched from <hi>Carelſtadt;</hi> with 2000 <hi>Croats</hi> and 1200 <hi>Valaques</hi> towards the Province of <hi>Corbavia,</hi> which he entred the 20th of <hi>July,</hi> and approached the Caſtle of <hi>Bunick,</hi> ſituate upon a Rock, having in it a Garriſon of 120 <hi>Turks,</hi> but upon the firſt Summons the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour capitulated, and came himſelf into the Camp to ſign the Capitulation which was, That he, and all that were in Garriſon with him, ſhould have liberty to march out with Bag and Baggage, and all their Moveables to be conducted to <hi>Whias,</hi> or any other place he ſhould chuſe. Whereupon the Caſtle was the ſame day ſurrendred, together with the Cannon, which, by virtue of the Capitulation, was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main there. The next day all the Chriſtian Slaves were put into the Hands of Count <hi>Herberſtein</hi> and Colonel <hi>Orſich,</hi> with two hundred men, took Poſſeſſion, whilſt another Party conducted the Garriſon to <hi>Whias,</hi> formerly the capital City of <hi>Croatia:</hi> After which, a great many Families of the <hi>Valaques</hi> came and ſurrendred themſelves, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to become Chriſtians. Having burnt the Caſtle of <hi>Bunick,</hi> not being able to keep it, as lying too far from the Frontiers; and nail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up three pieces of Cannon and three Mortars found there, the ways being inacceſſible for Carriage, the Count marched to a large Plain on the ſide of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>daina,</hi> from whence he ſent out Parties which burnt and plundered all the Towns and Villages, and cut down all the Corn and Forrage for many Miles in compaſs; ſo that that ſertile Province which the <hi>Turks</hi> poſſeſſed 140 years, is quite deſtroyed. And on the 29th of <hi>July</hi> the Count returned with a Booty of 600 Horſes, 1300 head of Cattel, and ſome thouſands of Sheep, and not having loſt one man in this Expedition; and the Chevalier <hi>Janco,</hi> as it had been agreed on, entred the Province of <hi>Leicea</hi> with the like Succeſs. But the like Succeſs at preſent held not with the <hi>Poles;</hi> for the Troops of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36171:15"/>that Kingdom drawing together but ſlowly, the <hi>Tartars</hi> had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to make Incurſions into the Countries of <hi>Podolia</hi> and the lower <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> who burnt and deſtroyed a great number of Towns and Villages, carrying away the Inhabitants, together with much Booty. But a right underſtanding ſoon after being had between that Crown and the <hi>Czars</hi> of <hi>Moſcovy;</hi> the latter giving the <hi>Coſſacks</hi> under their Protection, liberty to joyn and act with thoſe under the Protection of the former, a ſtop was put to thoſe Incurſions, and a great many <hi>Tartars</hi> who reiterated their Attempts, cut off. And the Sieur <hi>Lef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niskie</hi> being abroad with ſome Troops, fell upon a Party of <hi>Tartars</hi> who were ravaging the Country, killing 300 of them, and releaſing a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of Chriſtians, whom they were carrying into miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Bondage. Whereupon the Baſſa of <hi>Miedzibos</hi> writ to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the moſt conſiderable Places on the Frontiers of <hi>Poland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that Crown, to propoſe a reſtraint of all Incurſions on both ſides, ſeeing ſuch Enterpriſes only ruined the Countries, without any Advantage to the Princes their Maſters. Yet the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Forces towards the latter end of <hi>July,</hi> took the Field, and the Crown Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral took a review of them at <hi>Gliniani,</hi> where he found them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of 16000 Foot and 8000 Horſe, giving order for their decamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 29th of <hi>July,</hi> and marching to <hi>Viſia,</hi> near the <hi>Nieſter,</hi> there to continue till other Troops, who had not been able ſo ſoon to joyn them, came up, as thoſe of <hi>Lithuania,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Seraſquier Baſſa, upon his Defeat near <hi>Gran,</hi> having rallied his Troops, cauſed two Baſſa's, four Aga's, and ſome other Officers, who had not behaved themſelves well in the Battel, to be ſtrangled; and marching to <hi>Buda,</hi> paſſed the <hi>Danube,</hi> there giving out, That he would relieve <hi>Newheuſel</hi> whatever it coſt him; but upon the receipt of News that it was loſt, he formed a new Train of Artillery which he took out of <hi>Buda,</hi> and marched towards <hi>Vaccia,</hi> incaruping be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that place and <hi>Peſt;</hi> whereupon the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> repaſſed the <hi>Danube</hi> with the Imperial Army the 24th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> near <hi>Comor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> and advanced towards him: Upon which the Seraſquier having ſent a detached Party towards <hi>Agra,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Erla,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the <hi>Danube,</hi> with the Groſs of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, ſent an <hi>Aga</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to make ſome Overtures of Peace; to which his Highneſs anſwered; <hi>That he had no orders from the Emperor to treat of Peace; and that a victorious Army was not to be amuzed with ſuch Propoſals; and that he wondred the Seraſquier, after giving out that he was reſolved to fight the Chriſtians, did now avoid it by ſo baſty a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treas.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36171:16"/>To which the Aga replled. <hi>That the Country was ſo ruined on this ſide the</hi> Danube, <hi>that there was no Forrage for his Troops, and therefore he had been obliged to repaſs that River.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after the taking <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> in defending of which, according to the Report of the Priſoners, between 5 and 6000 <hi>Turks</hi> were kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. The Emperor appointed Count <hi>de Scherffenberg,</hi> Governour of it; into which the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> before had put a conſiderable Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, and ſummoned the Country-people to repair thither, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to clear the Works ruined during the Siege; cauſing, with all diligence, the Breaches to be repaired; and the Cannon, which, for the moſt part, were diſmounted, and lay, in a manner, buried in the Ruines, to be re-mounted, a great number of Carpenters and Maſons being ſent thither from <hi>Vienna;</hi> and beſides <hi>Vaccia</hi> and <hi>Novigrade,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> in ſome Conſternation abandoned <hi>Hatwan</hi> (a place of that Conſideration, that a Baſſa commanded there) which they did in ſo much haſte, that they had not time to demoliſh the Fortifications.</p>
            <p>The Serraſquier, upon his being deſerted by 6000 <hi>Tartars,</hi> who left him at his repaſſing the <hi>Danube,</hi> in order to their return home ſent back the Baſſa's of <hi>Temeſwar, Waradin,</hi> and <hi>Agria,</hi> with the Troops under their Command, to their reſpective Governments, and poſted himſelf with the reſt of his Forces between <hi>Buda</hi> and <hi>Alba Regalis;</hi> and now the danger being over on this ſide, the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> taking his leave of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and principal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the Army, departed for <hi>Vienna;</hi> where, on the 9th of <hi>September,</hi> he arrived, and was joyfully received.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were doing, General <hi>Scultz</hi> preſſed on the Siege of <hi>Eſperies,</hi> advancing to the Ditch, and placing his Galleries, doing great Execution with the Bomboys, and with the Cannon-ſhot, laying open a large Breach in the Wall; but the beſieged, in hopes of being relieved by Count <hi>Teckely,</hi> made an obſtinate defence, though his whole ſtrength conſiſted not in above 1500 men; a great part of thoſe that were in Arms with him having deſerted him upon the Publication of the Emperor's Pardon, wherein none were exempted that ſhould in time lay hold of that Clemency, and return to their Duty and Obedience (Count <hi>Teckely</hi> and two others excepted) which Pardon, the General, by the intimation of the Emperor, ſent an Officer to make known to the beſieged; but they not only refuſed to embrace it, but killed the Perſon that was ſent to communicate it to them: Upon notice of which, the General was ſo incenſed, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36171:16"/>he cauſed the Cannon to play inceſſantly upon the place, caſting a great many <hi>Bomboys</hi> into it; which beat down, and ruined many houſes. whereupon they hung out a White Flag, making ſigns to capitulate: But divers Officers approaching near, to underſtand what they had to ſay, they fired upon them, and killed ſome of them.</p>
            <p>The Vice-Roy of <hi>Croatia</hi> taking the advantage of the great conſternation the <hi>Turks</hi> were in, about the beginning of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> entred <hi>Boſnia</hi> with Five Thouſand men, plundering and brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divers Villages: So that in Four days March he came before <hi>Dubitza,</hi> a very rich Town, with a Caſtle adjoyning to it, on the River <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nna;</hi> which the <hi>Croats,</hi> with little oppoſition, made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of: And having poſſeſſed themſelves of a great deal of rich plunder, ſet fire to it: But they in the Caſtle giving the Alarm to the neighbouring places, the <hi>Turks</hi> haſtened from thence to their aſſiſtance: And having together formed a Body of about Fifteen Hundred men, they followed the <hi>Croats,</hi> and fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in the Rear, as they were retreating: But facing about, they ſo well received them, that between Four and Five Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Turks</hi> were killed, and the reſt put to flight. And in this Action the <hi>Croats</hi> took Seven Colours, which by the Officer that brought the News, were preſented to the Emperor. As for the Spoil they took, it was very great, conſiſting of Money and rich Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Series</hi> of ſucceſs on the part of the Imperialiſts, obliged <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> the <hi>Seraſquier Baſſa,</hi> to keep on the other ſide the <hi>Danube,</hi> with the Forces that remained under his Command: and where Force could not, he reſolved to try what Artifice could do: and thereupon diſpatched a Letter to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> by the <hi>Aga</hi> before mentioned; wherein he acquainted his Highneſs moreover, That he had full power from the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> to treat and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a Peace; which he prayed him in the Name of God to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, and content himſelf with the Honour he had gain'd, that an end might be put to the War which had ſpilt ſo much Blood, and cauſed the Ruin of many people; offering to abandon <hi>Teckely,</hi> and deliver to the Emperor his Hoſtages at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> But theſe Overtrues being uſual with the <hi>Infidels</hi> when they are ſucceſsleſs in their Wars, (they ſeldom keeping any League longer than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts with their advantage) it was not thought convenient to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon a Treaty, eſpecially at a time when <hi>Hungary,</hi> that Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36171:17"/>Kingdom, and Bulwark of Chriſtendom, is in ſo fair a way to be freed from the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Tyranny: Nor were the Pretences of <hi>Teckely</hi> any other ways reſented.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Poliſh</hi> Troops being abroad, the <hi>Sieur Demideski,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a Party in that Kingdom, having notice, that the <hi>Turks</hi> were marching to put a great Convoy into <hi>Caminiec,</hi> he drew out divers Troops, the better to ſtrengthen him from the neighbouring Garriſons; and ſent Orders to the <hi>Sieur Lesmiski,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſch,</hi> immediately to joyn him with the Forces of their Diviſion; which having done, they conjunctly marched to <hi>Cecchin;</hi> when near that place they were informed, That a Convoy, guarded by Five Thouſand <hi>Turks,</hi> under the Orders of <hi>Suin Baſſa,</hi> and two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s and Six Thouſand <hi>Tartars,</hi> under the Command of <hi>Biologrod,</hi> and all under the Command of their General <hi>Smailo,</hi> was got into <hi>Caminiec:</hi> and that after a ſhort refreſhment, dividing into Four Bodies, one marched towards <hi>Zablatiow,</hi> and the others to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Koſſow, Sniatin,</hi> and <hi>Romanow;</hi> from whence, having made Incurſions into <hi>Procutia,</hi> and <hi>Volinia,</hi> they re-joyned at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now;</hi> where they were attacked by a Detachment from the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Army, and intirely routed, upwards of Two Thouſand of them killed, and all their Baggage, together with the Booty they had got, taken; many of thoſe that eſcaped the Field, being likewiſe ſet upon by the Country-people, were ſlain.</p>
            <p>The Beſieged in <hi>Eſperies</hi> beginning to diſpair of being relieved by <hi>Teckely,</hi> and underſtanding 6000 men detached from that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, commanded by the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> were on their March, to joyn General <hi>Schultz:</hi> That the Beſiegers had placed their Galleries to the Wall; raiſing two Batteries on the Edge of the Ditch, and fixing their <hi>Miners</hi> to the Root of the Attack'd-Baſtion; as alſo, that Six Hundred men, whom <hi>Count Teckeley</hi> ſent to try if they could get into the place, had been routed. and divers of them killed, thought it high time to think of ſurrender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Important place. So that on the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>September</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour deſired a Parley, and a Ceſſation of Hoſtilities till the next, that in the mean time he might aſſemble the Inhabitants, to conſider about the Articles of Surrender; which General <hi>Schultz</hi> looking upon as a Deſign to gain time, refuſed to conſent to; demanding to have Two Officers immediately ſent to him, as Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtages. But to this the beſieged refuſing to comply, the firing from either ſide was renewed. But the next day the Governour
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36171:17"/>underſtanding the near approach of the Detachment from the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Army, again deſired a Parley, agreeing to ſend out a Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant and Two Burghers, upon condition the Beſiegers would give as many Hoſtages on their part: which being agreed on in the Morning, and accordingly performed in the Evening, the Capitulation was agreed on and ſigned. The chief Articles being theſe; <hi>viz. The Magiſtrates and Burghers ſhall enjoy their Privileges, and the Places and Employments they are at preſent poſſeſſed of: but that all the Inhabitants ſhall be diſarmed, and their Arms carried to the Town-houſe: That the Governour, and all the Officers, with ſuch of the Garriſon (which conſiſted of Three Hundred</hi> Germans, <hi>and Seven Hundred</hi> Hungarians) <hi>as deſired it, ſhould be received into the Emperor's Service, in the ſame quality they were then in; and that the reſt ſhould be conducted to ſome place as themſelves ſhould direct.</hi> Accordingly on the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> the City was ſurrendered, and the Governour, all the <hi>Germans,</hi> and moſt of the <hi>Hangarians</hi> entred into the Emperor's Service: the reſt, Ten or Twelve excepted, voluntarily promiſing to return home, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again bear Arms againſt his Imperial Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Teckely</hi> finding by the continual ſucceſs of the Imperialiſts in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungary,</hi> his Intereſt weakened; and that the <hi>Turks</hi> were in no condition to aſſiſt him, began to think of retiring, with his Baggage and Treaſure, into places of more ſafety: but being fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len upon in his March, he was routed by a Party of <hi>Croats;</hi> all, or the greateſt part of his Treaſure taken, and a great many of his Rebellious Party killed: So that he appeared not publickly in many days. Whereupon, beſides <hi>Tokay, Oneth, Potack,</hi> and <hi>Serentz, Palottz, Doronitz, Woldockin</hi> and <hi>Sparditz,</hi> ſurrendered, and were taken into the Imperial Protection: By which, and the like means moſt of the Towns in both the <hi>Hungaries</hi> are in the poſſeſſion of the Emperor. Nor on the part of the <hi>Venetians</hi> is the Succeſs leſs in taking <hi>Calamata</hi> and <hi>Zarnata,</hi> and defeating the Captain <hi>Baſſa,</hi> who advanced to the Relief of the former, with Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, killing a great many of them, and taking much Spoil: For which Victories, <hi>&amp;c. Te Deum</hi> was ſung in the Church of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> at <hi>Venice.</hi> The <hi>Poles</hi> likewiſe much about the ſame time routed two Parties of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> ſent out by the <hi>Seraſquier Solyman,</hi> to ravage the Country.</p>
            <p>The Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> (after having taken <hi>Zarnat</hi> and <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata,</hi> as likewiſe defeated the <hi>Turkiſh Captain Baſſa,</hi> who came
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36171:18"/>to ſuccour the Towns) marched towards <hi>Navarina;</hi> to which march the Baſſa rallying his broken Troops, endeavoured to put a Stop; but being warmly received by General <hi>Moroſini,</hi> 4000 of his Men were ſlain, and all the Cannon and Baggage taken. Much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame time the <hi>Vaivode Junco</hi> underſtanding that 3000 <hi>Turks</hi> were marching with a Deſign to plunder the Suburbs of <hi>Sebenico,</hi> laid an Ambuſh of <hi>1200 Morlaques,</hi> who fell upon them, putting the greateſt part to the Sword; which continual Current of Succeſs cauſed much Conſternation amongſt the Infidels in thoſe parts; and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by reaſon many of the ſmall Fortreſſes either ſurrender'd upon the firſt Summons, or after inconſiderable Reſiſtance; amongſt which are <hi>Porto Vitulo, Chieſiſa, Paſſava,</hi> and <hi>Portoquaglia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chaſcaw</hi> in the upper <hi>Hungary,</hi> conſiſting of a Garriſon of <hi>4000</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, the moſt reſolute of <hi>Teckely</hi>'s Party, refuſing the Imperial Amneſly, was beſieged by the Forces under the Command of Count <hi>Caprara;</hi> to relieve which, <hi>Teckely</hi> made ſome inconſiderable Attempts, but not finding himſelf ſtrong enough to force the Leaguers, <hi>Peterhaſi,</hi> one of his principal Commanders, under pretence of coming over to the Imperialiſts with 600 Horſe, and inſinuating a Deſign he had to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the beſieged to ſurrender, got into that ſtrong place, leaving his Baggage valued at 100000 Florins, as a Pledge of his Fidelity, in the Imperial Camp; but inſtead of performing his Promiſe, he, on the contrary, encouraged them to an obſtinate Defence; ſo that by the continual firing, and in divers Sallies a conſiderable number of men were killed on either ſide; yet upon News of Count <hi>Teckely</hi>'s being ſecured in Irons by the <hi>Turks,</hi> that important place ſurrendred: The account of which is thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Teckely</hi> finding himſelf too weak to defend that Place, on the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of which his hopes of keeping up his Credit with his Party, and longer continuance in the upper <hi>Hungary</hi> were founded, he ſent to the Baſſa of great <hi>Waradin</hi> to let him know what Danger it was in, urging the great Importance of te place, preſſing for ſpeedy Succour, in order to relieve it: And though in this caſe he doubted not to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, as appeared by his Letters intercepted, wherein he exhorted the beſieged to make a reſolute Defence, and expect Relief within twenty days. The Baſſa, the better to diſſemble what was intended, returned him this Anſwer; <hi>That he was not ignorant how much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned them to preſerve That Town, and that he would give him all the aſſiſtance he could.</hi> But about eight days after he ſent a Meſſage, acquainting him, That he could not furniſh him with the number of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36171:18"/>Men he required, by reaſon he had received other Orders from his Maſter the Grand Signior, of great Conſequence to the common Cauſe, which were not convenient to be communicated to him by Letter, and therefore deſired him to repair to <hi>Waradin,</hi> that he might inform him by word of mouth; and that he might not doubt his Security, he ſent him a Paſs-port, which ſo much confirmed him, that accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with <hi>Petrozzi,</hi> and ſome others his principal Adherents, he went with a Guard of five hundred Horſe, and was met by the Baſſa without the Gates, and by him received with all the appearance of Kindneſs and Eſteem. Being conducted into the Town with only eight of his Attendants as a ſeeming Welcome, all the Cannon was diſcharged, with other Marks of Reſpect. When the Baſſa having entertained him at Supper, and that ended, an Aga, with a Guard of <hi>Janizaries</hi> entred the Room, and told him, he had Orders from the Grand Signior to ſeize him, and carry him to <hi>Adrianople;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon cauſed Irons to be put upon his Hands and Feet. <hi>Petrozzi</hi> being preſent, the Baſſa told him, That the Grand Signior gave him the Principality and Command which <hi>Teckely</hi> had, and that he would aſſiſt him with all his Forces. To this he ſeemed to conſent, but being got out of the place, and coming to the five hundred Horſe that had attended <hi>Teckely</hi> thither, he told them what had happened, and withal exhorted them to return to that Obedience they owed the Emperor, as their Sovereign, and to put themſelves into his Service; which they conſenting to he marched at the Head of them directly to the Imperial Camp before <hi>Chaſcaw,</hi> ſending to the reſt of <hi>Teckely</hi>'s Party, with Admonition to follow the like Example, which they ſo readily conſented to, that his number by that time he entred the Camp, was increaſed to near 7000, to whom General <hi>Caprara</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Benefit of the Imperial Amneſty; and ſent <hi>Petrozzi</hi> into Chaſcaw to give the beſieged an Account of what had befaln <hi>Teckely,</hi> their Ring-leader, and the danger they were in, by reaſon of the Mines that were ready to be ſprung at the Foot of the Wall. Upon notice of which, they came to a Reſolve to ſurrender the place, which they did upon advantageous Articles, on the 25th of <hi>October</hi> 1685. when all the <hi>Germans</hi> that were in the place, to the number of 180, took the Oath of Fidelity, and were admitted into the Imperial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments; and ſuch <hi>Hungarians</hi> as deſired it, permitted to return to their reſpective Habitations. Following the Example of this ſtrong place, almoſt all the Towns in the upper <hi>Hungary</hi> ſurrendred; ſo that the Infidels have but narrow footing in that Kingdom. The King of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36171:19"/>
               <hi>Poland</hi> proſecuting his Succeſs, after ſix days skirmiſhing with the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> gave them Battle the 10th of <hi>October,</hi> and after five Hours diſpute, put them to flight, with great Slaughter, taking di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Priſoners of note, as likewiſe Standards, and the moſt part of their Baggage. This Victory was obtained, notwithſtanding the Enemies Army treble the number; nor were the <hi>Caſſacks</hi> in the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of that Crown, leſs active for beſieging <hi>Jarolick,</hi> a Town on the <hi>Nieſter;</hi> they took it, and put the Garriſon conſiſting of 1200 men moſtly to the Sword. And thus Rebellion loſt its aim, whilſt the Power of the Infidels is reduced to a <hi>Criſis:</hi> The whole <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire upon the ſenſe of ſuch reiterated Loſſes, being ready to mutiny; and turn all things into Confuſion: And now the Imperialiſts being moſtly gone into their Winter-quarters, we will conclude the Actions of this glorious Campaign.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
